<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Credible reportes from France, and Flanders In the moneth of May. 1590.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112646</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847892</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847892</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12956</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01151)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12956)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Credible reportes from France, and Flanders In the moneth of May. 1590.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 4-7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be solde by William Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Flanders --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12956:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12956:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12956:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CREDIBLE Reportes from France, and Flanders. In the moneth of May. 1590.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>VBIQVE FLORET</q>
               <byline>G. B.</byline>
               <figDesc>printer's mark of John Wolfe, McKerrow 242: deivce of a fleur-de-lis with cherubs at top, and a satyr and a human figure at foot</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſolde by</hi> William Wright. 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:12956:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12956:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Credible Reportes from France, and Flanders.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Weeke ſince, came from Diepe a certaine Bark the which arriued at Plymmouth which reported, that the gouernor of Diepe, was come to Diep after the battaile ſicke of an ague, and that during his ſicknes, the Papiſtes murmured, and woulde not ſuffer the exerciſe of Religion, conſpiring to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the towne: But the Gouernour being certified of their ill intent, did baniſhe out of the town about one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and twenty of them which were the authors of the conſpiracy, amongſt which are many of the chiefeſt and richeſt of the towns men, and many of their wiues, and the gouernour hath ſeaſed vppon their goods.</p>
            <p>Creſſy hath bene taken by the Marſhall Byrron: a man of Parris was their Captaine, whoſe name was Pierre, for whoſe raunſome was offered ſeuen hundreth Frenche Crownes, but the King cauſed him to be hangd, and fiue and twentie of the Chiefeſt with him.</p>
            <p>Beaumont ſur Oyſe hath beene taken by the Duke of <hi>Longueuille:</hi> there the Lord <hi>la Noe</hi> was hurt with a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabuſe in one of his thighes, but there is no perill: the duke of <hi>Longueuille</hi> neuertheleſſe hath cauſed the chiefeſt men of the Citty to be hanged.</p>
            <p>The Gouernour of Renes hath cauſed one friar to bee hanged, and halfe a doſen of the chiefeſt of the Citty, who did call the King hereticke.</p>
            <div n="Flanders" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:12956:4"/>
               <head>From Flanders.</head>
               <p>THe enemy battering the Skonce of Seuen Berghen with great fury on the fourth of this inſtant, a breache being made, they had firſt prouided a great ſhip to lie on the water, erecting a frame on the top of the maſt propped vp with other poſtes, where diuers Muskettiers were placed to beate our men from the breache, giuing an aſſault alſo at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtant with the choiſe men of their army, by chaunce fire ſalling from the top among certain poulder liyng in the ſhippe, ſpoiled them all, to the number of two hundreth that were aboue and below: which the aſſailants ſeeing, partly failing of corage (but in truth by the reſolution of our men) were repulſed. One other attempt was geuen, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion there was loſt of them in this ſeruice eight hundreth men, and thirteene Captaines of eſpeciall account, ſo that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> chiefe commander ther was enforced to retire with diſhonor. The ſelfe ſame day, it was our happe with our troupes of horſe to ouerthrow two hundreth of their beſt horſe, we hauing taken ſome fiue and thirty pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners and one hundreth &amp; forty horſes, the reſt being put to the ſword: the enemy maketh head againe at Furnholt, as it is thought for the reliefe of Numeghen, which our men haue beleagerd: the Duke of Parma continueth at Bruſſels full of infirmity and diſcontentments, the mindes of them all being ſo diuided, by reaſon of the continuing ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treds betweene the Spaniards and Italians, ſo amaſed with theſe daily miſfortunes, and ſo weakened by reaſon of many ouerthrowes we haue geuen them, as a very reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable force here, would worke no ſlender effects, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion diuert many other dangerous reſolutions.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Berghen vp Zoan <date>this fiftéenth of May. 1590.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="France" type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12956:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The late newes from France.</head>
               <p>THey of <hi>Paris</hi> haue made a ſally, in the which they haue loſt a great many of their men: The Duke <hi>de Nemors</hi> their gouernour, and brother to the Duke <hi>de Main,</hi> iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out of <hi>Paris</hi> with them, and as it is thought is ſlaine.</p>
               <p>The King doth proſper in all his actions.</p>
               <p>It is ſayd that the King hath taken <hi>Pontoiſe</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Denis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paris</hi> is in great diſtreſſe and in deſperation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rouen</hi> is in lyke ſort.</p>
               <p>The Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> is within <hi>Peronne,</hi> with verie ſmall hope of any great ſuccour.</p>
               <p>The King hath taken <hi>Giſors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Vigues</hi> had beſieged <hi>Ponterſon,</hi> and had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie made two breaches, the one of fiue and twentie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the other of fiftéene, and had giuen thrée aſſaults, in the which hee had bene repulſed, but hee hearing that the Earle of <hi>Torigny</hi> was comming with great force to rayſe vp his ſiege, he retyred within mount Saint <hi>Michael,</hi> and wrote his Letters to the Duke of <hi>Mercurie</hi> who was at <hi>Nantes,</hi> requiring him to come to his aide, for his honour and profites ſake, or elſe he ſhould be forced to yéeld</p>
               <p>He that carried the Letters, came ſtraight to the Earle of <hi>Torigny,</hi> who did ſée his Letters, &amp; ſent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coppy of it to the Prince of <hi>Ombes,</hi> who was betwéene Saint <hi>Malo</hi> and <hi>Vitre,</hi> and forthwith ſent the meſſenger to the Duke of <hi>Mercurie</hi> with his Letters, who after hee had ſéene them, did write by and by an anſwere to the Lorde <hi>Viques,</hi> and praied him to be ſtrong, ſaying, that within thrée dayes hée would come to his aide with thrée thouſand men, to the end that their forces being ioyned together, they might ſet vpon the Earle, being aſſured that he could not haue the helpe of the Prince, becauſe hee knew him to bee verie buſie in baſe Britaine. The meſſenger came againe to the Earle, and ſhewed him the anſwere of the letters, the coppies wherof were ſent to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince, who cauſed al the horſemen to march in haſt betwéen <hi>Nantez</hi> &amp; the Duke, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he did know that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12956:5"/> hee was out of <hi>Nantez,</hi> and when the Duke did knowe that he was betwéene two armies, hee ventured to fight with the Prince, but whiles they were fighting, the Earle came vpon him, and the Duke was there ſo ſore beaten, that he loſt ſeuentéene Enſignes and twelue hundred of his men, who were there ſlaine, beſides them that were taken and wounded, and hee himſelfe fled to a little Caſtle called <hi>Chaſteau Ioſſelin,</hi> in the which he is beſieged, and cannot long indure.</p>
               <p>This Caſtell Ioſſelin is in Britagnie, and is thought to be the ſtrongeſt place in the world, beeing a tower, builded vpon a high rocke, and almoſt not poſſible to be batterrd.</p>
               <p>When the Lord <hi>Vignes</hi> vnderſtood this, he yelded, and to make his peace, hee gaue to wife his daughter and onely heire, to the yonger brother of the Earle <hi>Montgomery,</hi> who was his priſoner, and kepte onely mount Saint <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> for the ſafetie of his perſon.</p>
               <p>The inhabitants of <hi>Dinau,</hi> which is the ſtrongeſt place of Britanie, hearing the diſcomfiture of the Duke, did chaſe out of their Citie their gouernour, who is the Dukes bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and did kill many of his men, amongſt which was the chiefe of his Captaines called Captaine <hi>Iean,</hi> and yéelded themſelues to the King.</p>
               <p>VVIthin the riuer of Bilbow, there are 4. great ſhips. In the Paſſage there are thirtéen great ſhips &amp; two pataches, that haue béene ready ſixe wéeks ſince, and haue ſtaied only for the Kings order: which was, that they ſhould with all ſpéed go to Saint Andrewes, there to take in men, biſket, and other prouoſion for the whole Fléete, and from thence preſently to go to <hi>Farole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>Farole</hi> there are ſixe Pinnaces, of ten and twelue tunnes a péece.</p>
               <p>It is ſuppoſed that the Kings force will be in this action one hundreth and fiftie ſailes, that is, thrée ſcore and ten, or foure ſcore great ſhips, eight gallies, foure galliaſſes, and thrée ſcore and ten, or thrée ſcore and fiftéene pataches and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12956:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> pinnaces of ſmall effect.</p>
               <p>It is ſayd alſo, that he hath cauſed to bee made certaine broad Boates, for the landing of men, which the ſhips ſhall drawe after them.</p>
               <p>There be thrée thouſand oares carried out of Biſkay to Farole.</p>
               <p>One hundreth Dutch gunners are come into Spaine, to go in this Fléete.</p>
               <p>Their greateſt want is Mariners and gunpouder, but they haue great ſtore of other prouiſion.</p>
               <p>The chiefeſt general in this Fléete, is <hi>Don Iuan de Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam,</hi> brother to the Marques of Saint a Cruce.</p>
               <p>For ſea Captaines of ſame, there be few or none: but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie and new found fellowes are allowed.</p>
               <p>The ſouldiers for this action are verie ſimple and vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in warres.</p>
               <p>The Fléete is appointed to come forth in the end of May, or about the tenth of Iune.</p>
               <p>The report is, that this Fléete ſhall go for Bel Ile, or for Nantz, and ſome ſaie, that it is onely to kéepe their owne coaſt, and not for England.</p>
               <p>There are in the Court of Spaine diuers Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, one is from the Duke <hi>de Maine,</hi> another from the Duke <hi>de Mercury,</hi> and another from the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> and another from the whole bodie of the League.</p>
               <p>They demand thrée millions of gold, and thirty thouſand men.</p>
               <p>There came of late to the Court of Spaine, an Iriſh man, about forty yeares of age, as Embaſſador, who was well receiued, and is well thought off: but what his buſines is, that is not knowen.</p>
               <p>There be ſixe thouſand Germans looked for in Spaine, about the end of May.</p>
               <p>It is ſayd that the king of Spaine is very ſicke, and it is thought that he will hardlie eſcape.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
